Rockefeller University records, Director, Herbert Spencer Gasser, Subject Files, Series 4 FA813
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Director, Herbert Spencer Gasser, Subject Files, Series 4
1935-1953
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA813
0.88 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
2 boxes.
Related Archival Materials note
Herbert Spencer Gasser was Director of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research 1935-1953. During his tenure he continued many of the administrative routines which had been established during the directorship of Simon Flexner. Thus, much administrative correspondence, in particular, matters dealing with personnel and administration of the physical plant are to be found in the papers of the Business Manager, Edric B. Smith, who served also, as Secretary of the Board of Trustees.
See FA137 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Subject Files, Series 3. See FA809 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Series 4.
Biographical/Historical note
Herbert Spencer Gasser, 1888-1963, physiologist, was Director of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1935-1953. His early work at the University of Wisconsin and at Washington University was done on circulation and respiration, including the mechanism through which the heart is accelerated in exercise and the rate of decreased oxidation in the respiratory center. Later at Washington University and at Cornell University Medical College his major interest was in the physiology of nerve, developing electrophysiological techniques through the development of vacuum tube amplification and the cathode ray oscillograph. In collaboration with Joseph Erlanger, also of Washington University, he developed an exhaustive determination of the constants of nerve fibers and the classification of nerve fibers in accordance with their properties. The two men shared the Nobel Prize in Medicine and Physiology in 1944 for this work.
Biographical Note
1888 Born July 5 Platteville, Wisconsin
1907 Graduate State Normal School of Wisconsin, Platteville
1910 A.B. University of Wisconsin
1911 A.M. University of Wisconsin
1911-1912 Assistant in physiology University Wisconsin
1912-1913 Instructor in physiology, University Wisconsin
1915 M.D. Johns Hopkins University Medical School
1915-1916 Instructor in pharmacology, University Wisconsin
1916-1918 Instructor in physiology, Washington University St. Louis
1918-1920 Associate in physiology, Washington University
1920-1921 Associate Professor in physiology, Washington University
1921-1931 Professor in pharmacology, Washington University
1923-1925 Study abroad: University College, London; National Institute of Medical Research, London; Sorbonne, Paris; University of Munich
1931-1935 Professor physiology, Cornell University Medical College New York, New York
1935-1953 Director, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York, New York
1953 June, retired as Director; returned to work in his laboratory; Member Emeritus RIMR
1963 Died May 11 New York Hospital, New York, N.Y. Cremated; ashes sent to sister. Interred family plot, Platteville, Wis.
Prizes
1944 Nobel Prize in Physiology and Medicine Shared with Dr. Joseph Erlanger
1954 Kober Medal, Association of American Physicians
Clubs Sigma Xi, Gamma Alpha, Alpha Omega Alpha, Century Club, Quadrangle Club
Honorary Degrees
1936 D. Sc. university of Pennsylvania
1940 D. Sc. University of Rochester
1940 LL. D. Washington University
1941 D. Sc. University of Wisconsin
1945 D. Sc. Columbia University
1947 LL. D. Johns Hopkins University
1947 D. Sc. Oxford University
1948 D. Sc. Harvard University
1949 Doctor Honoris Causa, Université Libre de Bruxelles
1949 Doctor of Medicine, Honorary. Université Catholique de Louvain
1953 Honorifique de docteur. Université de Paris
1959 D. Sc. The Rockefeller University
Served
1918 Pharmacologist, Chemical Warfare Service
1936 Johnson Foundation Lecturer, University of Pennsylvania
1937- Rockefeller Foundation Trustee
1937- Russell Sage Institute of Pathology. Board of Directors
1941- Princeton University. Dept. of Biology
1941-1944 National Defense Research Committee Division 9
1945 Research Board for National Security (Member)
1947 Massachusetts General Hospital, Scientific Advisory Committee
Member of American Societies, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Fellow, American Association for the Advancement of Science, Fellow, American Neurological Association (Associate Member), American Philosophical Society, American Physiological Society, American Society of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics, American Society of Electroencephalography (Honorary), Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease, Association of American Physicians, Harvey Society (Councilor, Vice President, President), History of Science Society, National Academy of Sciences, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine (Pres. 1937-1939), New York State Society for Medical Research (Active Member, 1952), Foreign Societies, Academie Royale de Médecine de Belgique, correspondence member, Accademia della Scienze dell'Istituto di Bologna, correspondence member, Asociación Médica Argentina, Honorary Member, Finnish Academy of Sciences, Honorary Foreign Member, Physiological Society (British) Honorary Member, Royal Society of Edinburgh, Honorary Member, Royal Society of London, Honorary Member, Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences, Foreign Member, Sociedad Argentina de Biologia, Honorary Member, Société Philomathique de Paris, Corresponding Member
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Herbert Spencer Gasser collection was deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives by The University.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 302-4
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Other Finding Aids
FA143 Rockefeller University records, Herbert Spenser Gasser, Correspondence, Series 2.
FA814 Rockefeller University records, Herbert Spenser Gasser, Biography, Series 6.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Medical research; Medical sciences; Viruses -- Research; Physiology; Princeton University; Rockefeller University; Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Flexner, Simon; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.)
- Subject files, 1935-1953; 4; 2 boxes
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  Scope and Contents note
  Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Director's subject file.
  One archive box of about five inches consists of materials originally arranged in a subject sequence in the Director's office.
  - Annual Scientific Reports (Box 1)
    - Abstracts made for Director's Report
    - Summaries covering 13 years, 1939-1951; Handwritten, penciled
      Not all the dates are clear. 2 sets undated (possibly 1939, 1940); 1941, 1942,1943, 1944, Apr. 1945, 1946, Apr. 1947, 1948, 1949, 1950, 1951.
  - Cole, Rufus (Box 1)
    - Biographical data. Minute adopted by Board of Trustees, RIMR on Cole retirement; Press release on Cole retirement. Typescript copy of address made by Dr. Gasser at Cole retirement dinner, 1937 May 13
  - Commission on Neurotropic Virus Diseases, 1942-1945 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence between Dr. Gasser, Mr. Debevoise Edric Smith and Francis G. Blake for War Department and John R. Paul for War Department and Yale Medical School on contract involving work of Peter Olitsky Leslie Webster and A. Sabin
  - Copyrights (Box 1)
    - Permissions granted from Journal Experimental Medicine
  - Debevoise, Thomas M., 1939-1952 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence which deals with press reports of retirements of Alexis Carrel and others; New York State Society for Medical Research and anti-vivisection legislation; Princeton sale; by-law changes as to outside compensation for Institute personnel or emeriti; function of the budget committee; tax exemptions as an educational institution; the Winterberg bequest
  - Flexner, Simon (Box 1)
    Deals with S.F.'s last illness and addresses for Memorial Meeting. Correspondence with Judge Learned Hand, Peyton Rous, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and Raymond Fosdick. Includes copy of address by G. Ramon (Institut Pasteur) and sent by secretary of Academic des Sciences, Paris.
  - Lavoisier painting by David (Box 1)
    - Requests to borrow
  - League of Nations, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence from Princeton University, Institute for Advanced Study, RIMR Princeton inviting science sections of League to take up residence in Princeton for duration of the war
  - Little, Ralph B., 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence between Dr. Gasser and the University of Pa. arranging a work situation for Ralph B. Little veterinarian, after closing of Princeton labs
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1951-1956 (Box 1)
    Primarily nominations and voting for new members. Includes bibliography and evaluation for D.W. Woolley nomination and 1952 telegram announcing election to membership of P.D. McMaster and D.W. Woolley. 1962 October 10 letter granting H.S. Gasser emeritus status.
  - Princeton Integration with New York City Laboratories, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - History
      Copies of materials from the files of J.D. Rockefeller including correspondence with Seth Low (president of Columbia University) and letters written to him by T.M. Prudden and W.H. Welch when queried about usefulness of developing a research institute modeled after the Pasteur Institute in the United States. Materials brought together to help understand the original thinking in developing RIMR in New York City. Handwritten summary by H.S. Gasser.
    - Notes
      Considerations for integration. Background notes of considerations leading to 2 May 1947 Trustee action to move toward integration. Includes 1943 6 page N.R.S. (Norman Stoll) holograph reporting on conference with C.T. (Carl TenBroeck). Handwritten notes by HSG evaluating the scientific work of the Institute at Princeton to determine what could not have been carried on in New York City; notes on factors to be considered in making a move to NYC; copy of property appraisal in NYC by Douglas Gibbons; copy of 1947 report requested by JDR, Jr. of HSG for an evaluation of how best to insure financial stability for the Institute's continued productivity.
    - Procedure, 1947 May-1950
      Copy of H.S. Gasser 1947 report to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Gasser correspondence with Carl TenBroeck (19 items), Richard Shope, John H. Northrop, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Harold W. Dodds (President of Princeton). Notes on meetings with Carl Ten Broeck, Northrop, and Shope and joint letter from Princeton Dept. employees reacting to integration decision. Copy of Separation Benefits established by RI for those employees to be terminated in move; notes and plans on moving benefits.
  - Princeton sale, 1947-1951 (Box 1)
    - Primarily correspondence with Lindsley F. Kimball in regard to sale of Princeton property after integration with New York City laboratories voted. Final sale in 1951 to Princeton University for James Forrestal Research Center in jet propulsion and related sciences
  - Promotion summaries, 2 folders (Box 1)
    2 folders which consist of summary of scientific work, some letters of recommendation, in some instances list of publications and a short biography is included.
    - A-K
      - Archibald, Reginald (by Donald Van Slyke)
      - Braun, Armin C. (by L.O. Kunkel; H.S. Gasser)
      - Chang, Hsiang-Tung
      - Chase, Merrill W.
      - Dole, Vincent
      - Goebel, Walther F. (handwritten by H.S. Gasser)
      - Granick, Sam (handwritten summary by H.S. Gasser)
      - Hirsch, James G.
      - Hotchkiss, Rollin Douglas (biography, bibliography, handwritten presentation for membership)
      - Hunt, Carlton C. (bibliography, biography, summary)
      - Kunitz, Moses (biography, handwritten summary, photo of crystals)
      - Kunkel, H.G. (biographical sketch, summary of scientific work and covering letter by T.M. Rivers)
    - L-W
      - Lancefield, R.C. (biog. sketch; summary of work to 1942)
      - Lloyd, David P.C. (handwritten evaluation by HSG)
      - Longsworth, Lewis G. (biog., biblio, summary of work)
      - Lorente de No, R. (handwritten summary by HSG)
      - Maramorosch, Karl
      - Merrifield, R.B. (Promotion recommended by D.W. Woolley)
      - Mirsky, A.E. (Direction of work and papers published)
      - Murphy, James S. (Recommendation by J.H. Northrop)
      - Palade, G. (biography and summary of work by HSG)
      - Porter, K.R. (biography and summary of work by HSG)
      - Schmitt, F.O. Handwritten presentation by HSG of desirability of building a department for the study of cellular organization. Provoked by unsuccessful attempt to bring F.O. Schmitt to RI
      - Shaw, Elliott (Biography, bibliography and summary of work at RI)
      - Shedlovsky, Theodore
      - Stern, Herbert (recommendation by A.E. Mirsky)
      - Tallen, Harris H. (recommendation by Moore and Stein)
      - Tamm, Igor (summary of work)
      - Wood, Harrison F. (summary of work)
      - Barry, Guy (recommendation by Walther Goebel)
      - Jesaitis, Margeris (recommendation by Walther Goebel)
  - Secretary's file, 1935-1952 (Box 1)
    Miss Von der Osten and Miss von Berg were both secretary to Dr. Gasser during this period. The file consists primarily of copies of letters sent to Dr. Gasser from his secretary while he was away from the office, either on professional business or on vacation. Includes his letter to his secretary informing her of his addresses en route or giving certain instructions.
    Included are 28 pages of assorted items; notes, packing slips, instructions from the period 1954-1961 when laboratory was run with the aid of a technician.
  - Addition to collection, circa 4", (5" Letter) (Box 2)
    H.S. Gasser material found in inactive files of the RU Corporate Secretary/Faculty Administrator.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Received February 1987 from Ms. Lila J. Magie.
    - Biographical material, 1964 November (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes 1935 news release re Directorship and HSG biography; RI obituary and reprint of Bio. Mem. of Fell. Roy. Soc., Nov 1964, Vol. 10.
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Includes re Directorship (1935); Nobel Prize (1944); death (1963); Robert Peter Coin (1965).
    - Photographs. Portraits, Nobel medal and citation (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Report on future needs of RIMR, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Bronk, Detlev W., 1944-1967
        - 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
          [See Mabel Bright/C. Belknap, 8 Jan 1964, folder 8 below].
        - 1956-1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - 1964-1965 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Carter and Jones, Insurance, 1937-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Flinn, Waldo F., 1935-1965
        - 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - 1937-1955 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Smith, E.B., 1935-1956
        - 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - 1941-1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - 1947-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Laboratory expenses, circa 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)